[Narrator (Brian Khuu?)] Hi, and welcome to the Designing Open Democracy podcast.
[Narrator (Brian Khuu?)] What we will be showing you is a retrospective recording of an event that we held on Friday 19th of May 2017 at Ross House.
[Narrator (Brian Khuu?)] The event topic was, What are the present and future challenges for democracy?
[Narrator (Brian Khuu?)] This will be a summary of the whole event, where we ask everybody at the end of the event to provide at least a short description about what they thought about the challenges of democracy and how they feel it could be addressed.
[Narrator (Brian Khuu?)] These days, we have a newer microphone, which sounds better.
[Narrator (Brian Khuu?)] But this recording, since it was a few years old, is not as good.
[Narrator (Brian Khuu?)] So just keep that in mind.
[Narrator (Brian Khuu?)] But aside from that, I hope you enjoy the 15-minute summary.
[Nick Merange?] Is there any way that there's an opportunity here?
[Nick Merange?] I would like to ask you, can you go around the table, or whoever is participating in tonight's session, and sort of list personally what we feel might be challenges to the present democracy, let alone future democracy, you can separate them.
[Nick Merange?] It doesn't matter about right and wrong, it's got nothing to do with that.
[Nick Merange?] It's more about how your feelings are into what you perceive.
[Unidentified] I like that.
[Tom Sesselman?] Well, I think I already sort of mentioned it, is that I think that the power that corporations have in politics is obviously one of the biggest issues, I think, is facing democracy today, and...
[Nick Merange?] Do you think this is something that will, like, is something that will also be a future challenge for democracy, or will be the biggest future challenge for democracy, or do you think that might shift to something else?
[Tom Sesselman?] Possibly.
[Tom Sesselman?] I mean, the problem is...
[Tom Sesselman?] Look, I haven't really been following politics so...
[Tom Sesselman?] I haven't really started following politics about, you know, like, about a year ago.
[Tom Sesselman?] I mean, I don't even really know about the history of politics as much as I say you guys might know.
[Tom Sesselman?] So I don't know if corporations have even had a big role in politics in the past, you know, 50 or 60 years.
[Tom Sesselman?] All I know is that at the moment, I think, there seems to be a lot of power going towards corporations.
[Tom Sesselman?] Yeah, in the future, yeah, I mean, I can't really see corporations losing power anytime in the new future without some sort of drastic change in politics.
[Kevin Woods] What about a desired future?
[Kevin Woods] How about we work on a desired future of how you envision a democracy?
[Kevin Woods] It doesn't matter what it might be, it's whether you see what you just said in a desired vision, an envision of what the future do you...
[Nick Merange?] Can we say that?
[Nick Merange?] I love that question, but can we have that for another...
[Nick Merange?] We've got 10 minutes left for the discussion.
[Nick Merange?] We do not have time to tackle that question tonight, but we will definitely discuss that in future sessions, thank you for that question, Kevin.
[Nick Merange?] So we'll move on to Francisco.
[Nick Merange?] Biggest challenge basically.
[Francisco] Biggest challenge, this moment, this engagement, misleading of the information, and populism.
[Francisco] Those are the three main problems that I can see this time in democracy and in history.
[Francisco] Now, the future, I would like to think optimistically about it, but if we keep going in the same route that we are going now, we are absolutely fucked.
[Nick Merange?] No, but once you think that the challenge is, in what way will we be fucked, if I may put it that way?
[Nick Merange?] Like, what are the future challenges that we should be addressing to minimize the chance that we'll be fucked?
[Francisco] We will be fucked.
[Francisco] Well, as you can see, in most of the world now, there are a lot of populist leaders leading the country.
[Francisco] Basically, that means that they have highly conflict of interest and they have highly problems of credibility and basically transparency.
[Francisco] And because of that, the fact of point that is coming from there is that they do whatever they want to do, and those things that they do, they are not aligned at all with what most of the people want in this time.
[Francisco] So when you have that kind of situation, sorry, the thing that is going to happen basically is that because they do whatever they want to do, they are not accountable to the people, they don't give a fuck, you know, and the result basically is going to be a disaster.
[Francisco] Like you can see now between two main men in the world now, that is Kim Jong-un and Donald Trump, and both of them, they have to deal with each other.
[Francisco] And those guys, they are not democratic persons.
[Francisco] They are not leaders in the liberal progressive way.
[Francisco] They are populists.
[Francisco] One is a dictator, and the other one is a populist.
[Francisco] And that's the result that we are going to keep having if more countries keep having populist leaders in their system.
[Francisco] In the optimistical way, I think that I have faith in humanity, and I think that we can be smarter enough to start creating a social change now that can allow us to create a certain truth that basically is what John Lennon was saying, power to the people.
[Francisco] So we can have a true democracy.
[Francisco] That's what it means.
[David?] Just quickly, to remove the economic slavery, the financial slavery that although it's been around for a long time, but can easily be removed in many, many countries, and probably all over the world.
[David?] Although the human rights lawyers want certain things, comprehensively, it should be in most, or should be in all constitutions of the countries, ingrained human rights and natural law rights, which encompass as many areas.
[David?] I'll leave it there, because there's many topics.
[David?] The biggest challenges that I'm going to tell you is that if we start with just simple principles, one of the principles in our democratic system, supposedly, was referendums.
[David?] And one of the key things just out of referendum is there's a massive amount of belief systems around not only a process of a referendum, let alone the result of a referendum, let alone how a referendum should be adhered to or whatever.
[David?] Those processes and belief systems around a referendum have really played a major role with what I would call if government's meant to play an element of a leader and how we perceive a leader that will only be one human being or 20 human beings, to me, they are there as a guide to other people to look up to.
[David?] And in that sense, a referendum, like all forms of their responsibilities, they have not adhered to their level of responsibilities that they claim they may have.
[David?] That is only one part of a major challenge because it's right behind the democratic process.
[David?] Another one that I would say is, once again, the amount of disparateness there is, let alone the amount of disconnection and the degree of disconnection that many people have with understanding the purpose, the roles, the responsibilities, the direction, and the future where everything is going.
[David?] I'll leave it at those two.
[Nick Merange?] Cool.
[Nick Merange?] Thank you.
[Nick Merange?] And Brian.
[Brian Khuu] Oh, hi.
[Brian Khuu] I think the biggest thing that is facing democracies in general, as I probably mentioned in the beginning, well, probably before the recording, is the issue of information overload.
[Brian Khuu] We are just self-led with so much information that we, like, that may be true or false, that we can't possibly make the right decision.
[Brian Khuu] And so, part of the things that I've seen online, which I think is a very interesting way to approach information overload, is through social media websites like Reddit, or through experimental argument mapping websites like Argument.
[Brian Khuu] And all these different ways of representing information, or filtering information, may, if it encompasses with, or joined with other kind of technologies which allows us to vote, and also think they're correct way, might allow us to actually have a full, or at least better control over the kind of people we filter into our position of power, or the decision making that filters into law.
[Brian Khuu] So, that's the way I see it.
[Nick Merange?] Cool.
[Nick Merange?] And, yeah, Andrew.
[Andrew Downing] Trust.
[Andrew Downing] Trust is a big one.
[Andrew Downing] Discourse between opposing sides, public forums, that sort of thing.
[Andrew Downing] A lot of the rest of all can sort it itself out if you just deal with those ones.
[Andrew Downing] The economic disparities, I think, ultimately fall, by the way, so either people cooperate, they cooperate based on trust.
[Andrew Downing] So that's just fundamental.
[Unidentified] What systems for that, please?
[Unidentified] Yeah.
[Unidentified] Interesting.
[Nick Merange?] Well, I guess slightly connected to that is the idea of like blockchain as a trustless system.
[Nick Merange?] So-
[Andrew Downing?] It's a distributed trust system.
[Andrew Downing?] Okay.
[Nick Merange?] Well, yeah, it's interesting because Nicola definitely describes it as trustless.
[Nick Merange?] And she's writing, I wish she was here to talk about it because she's writing a PhD on the future of trust.
[Nick Merange?] So-
[Andrew Downing?] Yeah, I don't like describing it as trustless.
[Andrew Downing?] Trust is still involved.
[Andrew Downing?] It's just, it's a distributed trust mechanism rather than a centralized one.
[Andrew Downing?] Okay.
[Nick Merange?] I guess it's trustless in the sense that you don't need to worry about it because it gets to the person you send it to and you don't have to-
[Andrew Downing?] An entity involved.
[Andrew Downing?] Yeah?
[Andrew Downing?] In a centralized institution, it can become corrupt and then you can't trust it anymore.
[Andrew Downing?] Instead, the distributed trust systems mean that, well, either everybody collectively has a common interest and you can trust in that, or if you can't trust in that, well, you're there anyway, so.
[Nick Merange?] Yeah, yeah, cool.
[Nick Merange?] Yeah, I like that term.
[Nick Merange?] Yeah.
[Nick Merange?] No, that might be something I kind of discuss with her, or we could discuss it on the channel, because that's an interesting kind of discussion.
[Nick Merange?] I don't know enough about it, but yeah, just wanted to bring up that perspective.
[Nick Merange?] And for me, I think the problem is in rationality, actually.
[Nick Merange?] Well, it's similar to coronation problems, but it's the idea of confirmation bias.
[Nick Merange?] It's like these psychological cognitive biases that we all have, and that, in combination with incentives, that actually pull us away from cooperation systematically, means that it's basically just a tragedy of society, that it can never be a utopia, because...
[Unidentified] Tragedy of the commons.
[Nick Merange?] Yeah, tragedy of the commons is based off this idea, because individuals have different interests individually to the collective.
[Nick Merange?] Like, if...
[Nick Merange?] And if one person defects, then, like, everything else kind of falls away.
[Nick Merange?] So it only needs one person to kind of defect from a prisoner's dilemma scenario, for it to be always, you know, better to defect.
[Nick Merange?] So then you have no cooperation whatsoever.
[Nick Merange?] And that's not really anyone's fault.
[Nick Merange?] That's just people acting, like, in their own rational self-interest, but everyone would be worth soft if they could somehow, like, agree, but they won't agree because of these individual incentives that we all face.
[Nick Merange?] So because there are limited amounts of resources, we have to allocate them, you know, there's trade-offs.
[Nick Merange?] And so we have to kind of, like, compete for those resources.
[Nick Merange?] So it's effectively competition is the problem, and we can't get away from competition because there's finite amounts of resources.
[Nick Merange?] So I think, I just think those are the, I think they're hard, like, I think they're impossible problems to solve.
[Nick Merange?] But we should acknowledge them, and maybe there are hacks for, you know, using empathy or using some other kind of method to kind of connect with other people.
[Nick Merange?] These nation-states are a big, important invention, in my view, and in getting people to cooperate who otherwise wouldn't have.
[Nick Merange?] So we're able to do that through our psychological makeup as group-like kind of beings who have evolved in groups.
[Nick Merange?] So that kind of allows us to get beyond that stuff.
[Nick Merange?] So, yeah, I guess it's both those things, and yeah.
[Unidentified] Tough.
[Nick Merange?] I think it's interesting to see that we've all got different answers to this one question.
[Nick Merange?] Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[Nick Merange?] Yeah, I think that's good.
[Nick Merange?] Yeah, sorry.
[Nick Merange?] Excellent.
[Kevin Woods or David?] In general, most of the topics we've discussed just before are actually all linked.
[Kevin Woods or David?] Oh, yeah.
[Kevin Woods or David?] To the same goal, technically, what we're all saying.
[Kevin Woods or David?] It's for equality, fairness, and it just comes down to being a human, you know.
[Kevin Woods or David?] Bring purpose back for all people to understand their positioning and why they live in the community.
[Kevin Woods or David?] Bring purpose back to community.
[Kevin Woods or David?] Bring purpose back for people's role in government.
[Kevin Woods or David?] That is, bring the governance, and I'll give you one thing that we're working on.
[Kevin Woods or David?] Bring the government, governance, the whole governance of the whole system back into the communities to have, for the first time, full self-governing communities.
[Kevin Woods or David?] That's all I will say.
[Nick Merange?] Okay, yeah, cool.
[Nick Merange?] That's one way to definitely increase, deal with a couple of these ideas of engagement.
[Nick Merange?] It's people's responsiveness, people's participation, all the stories under the sun.
[Nick Merange?] Yeah, yeah, cool.
[Nick Merange?] Nice.
[Nick Merange?] Thanks for sharing that with us.
[Nick Merange?] Thanks everyone for coming today.
[Nick Merange?] Thanks for everyone who's potentially listening to this podcast.
[Nick Merange?] Thank you, Tom, Francisco, David, Kevin, Brian, Andrew.
[Nick Merange?] Yeah.
[Unidentified] Thanks to you, Nick.
[Nick Merange?] Thank you very much.
[Nick Merange?] And yeah, we'll see you next time.
[Nick Merange?] Thanks, everyone.
[Narrator (Brian Khuu?)] So thank you for listening to the end of this retrospective podcast for Designing Open Democracy on the summary of challenges facing the present and future of democracy.
[Narrator (Brian Khuu?)] If you have any feedback, we will be eager to hear what you say.
[Narrator (Brian Khuu?)] So you could contact us at contact at designingopendemocracy.com or you could reach us at our reveal page.
[Narrator (Brian Khuu?)] So thanks for listening and have a nice day.